Andrew Hendrickson Papers
Andrew Hendrickson Papers
1925-1971
1948-1967
Hendrickson, Andrew, 1899-
10.5 linear ft.
Consists of correspondence, reports, printed material, and memorabilia, including certificates, plaques, and photographs. The collection includes material generated by Herschel W. Nisonger (predecessor), William Dowling (successor), and Andrew Hendrickson during their tenures as professors of adult education at Ohio State University, however the bulk of the material belongs to Hendrickson (1947-1967). Correspondents whose letters are of significant depth and duration include: William D. Dowling, John B. Holden, Cyril O. Houle, Glenn S. Jensen, Homer Kempfer, Malcolm S. Knowles, Burton W. Kreitlow, Fern Long, Robert A. Luke, Herschel W. Nisonger, Newton C. Rochte, and Coolie Verner. Part 2, added in 1991, contains miscellaneous pamphlets, additional memorabilia, and some material relating to the Adult Education Association (AEA), the National Association of Public School Adult Educators (NAPSAE), and the National Education Association (NEA).
149046
Biographical History
Born November 17, 1899, in Pedrickstown, New Jersey, Andrew Hendrickson earned an A.B. in English from Bucknell University in 1925, an M.A. in English from Columbia University in 1935, and the Ph.D. in adult education from Columbia in 1943. He served as head of the English Department in the Cliffside Park, New Jersey, High School and taught social studies in the Westfield, New Jersey, High School and the New York City Regents Evening High School.
Hendrickson served as Assistant and Associate in adult education as well as instructor in sociology at the Teachers College of Columbia University and was an assistant professor of adult education as well as Director of Cooperative Education and Assistant Dean at Cleveland College of Western Reserve University. In 1947 Hendrickson went to Ohio State University as professor of Education, where in 1957 he was appointed director of the Center for Adult Education. Retiring from Ohio State in 1967, Dr. Hendrickson became director of the Institute of Senior Adults and professor of adult education in the Department of Adult Education at Florida State University.
Andrew Hendrickson was a member and vice president of the National Education Association. He served on the executive committee and as a member of the Delegate Assembly of the Adult Education Association. A past secretary-treasurer of the Ohio Association for Adult Education, Dr. Hendrickson was editor of the journal of that organization, The Ohio Adult Observer, from 1948 to 1960. He was also one of the founders and the first president of the Adult Education Council of Greater Columbus, Ohio.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Andrew Hendrickson Papers arose primarily from Hendrickson's work at Ohio State University. All of the material came from the office of the professor of adult education at Ohio State. This material is almost exclusively Hendrickson's, but most of the material dated before 1947 resulted from the work of Hendrickson's predecessor, Herschel W. Nisonger. There is also correspondence from 1967 generated by William D. Dowling, Hendrickson's successor. The collection consists of correspondence, printed material including reproduced material and published material, and a few photographs. The inclusive dates of the collection are 1933-1971 but the bulk of the papers are dated between 1948 and 1967.
The collection arrived in two parts separated by nearly twenty years, and the two parts were treated separately.
Part 1 material is divided into three categories: correspondence, writings, and miscellaneous material. Correspondence covers the period 1937-1967, with emphasis on 1948-1967, and includes both incoming and outgoing letters, telegrams, and memoranda. The material is arranged chronologically with multiple items having the same date arranged alphabetically by the correspondents' names. Undated material is placed at the end of the section. Significant correspondents (those for whom there are at least twenty pieces in the collection) and the inclusive dates of their letters follow. In no case are there more than fifty pieces for any individual.
Dowling, William D., 1967
Bolden, John Bernard, 1943-1964
Houle, Cyril Orvin, 1958-1966
Jensen, Glenn S., 1959-1967
Kempfer, Homer Hadley, 1947-1966
Knowles, Malcolm S., 1951-1966
Kreitlow, Burton, 1950-1967
Long, Fern, 1948-1967
Luke, Robert A., 1946-1966
Nisonger, Herschel W., 1937-1962
Rochte, Newton C., 1949-1963
Verner, Coolie, 1953-1965
The inclusive dates of Writings are 1933-1969. Included in this category are articles and addresses, reports and proposals, copies of The Ohio Adult Observer, and student papers from Hendrickson's classes. There are eleven articles and addresses, arranged alphabetically by title. Reports and proposals include documents prepared by Hendrickson or by committees of which Hendrickson was a member. These are arranged chronologically with undated pieces placed at the end of the section. Since Hendrickson was an editor of The Ohio Adult Observer, there is a fairly complete run of this journal between the dates 1933 and 1966. Student papers are arranged chronologically.
Miscellaneous material, 1945-1967, comprises biographical information on Hendrickson and Nisonger; meeting papers, including working papers, minutes and proceedings; memorabilia, including membership lists and rosters, photographs, programs, brochures, newspaper clippings, and a script; and unidentified pieces. Minutes include reports of only those meetings which Hendrickson attended and are arranged chronologically. Transcripts of meetings of the Commission of Professors of Adult Education for 1957 to 1959 are arranged chronologically in the section of proceedings. The CPAE, a branch of the Adult Education Association of the United States of America, was organized to develop a philosophy of adult education. Membership lists and rosters name members of organizations and rosters of conference and meeting participants. These lists are arranged chronologically, with undated material at the end of the section. The few photographs are mostly of meetings; they are undated and unidentified. The section of programs includes printed programs of meetings and conferences in which Hendrickson participated. The programs are arranged chronologically, and undated material is placed at the end of the section. The brochure relates to the program and services of the Bureau of Special and Adult Education at Ohio State University. The newspaper clippings describe the retirement of Herschel W. Nisonger. The script is of a skit performed at an appreciation banquet for Nisonger upon his retirement. Unidentified material is arranged chronologically.
Part 2 consists of miscellaneous pamphlets on various adult education topics, as well as a few documents reflecting Hendrickson's involvement with several adult education organizations. This group of materials date from the late 1920s to the early 1960s, with the 1950s and 1960s predominating.
Materials from Part 2 are organized by subject area into four groups: Adult education - general contains a selection of adult-education related topics. Adult education organizations comprises material such as reports, minutes, and programs related to the American Association for Adult Education (AAAE), the Adult Education Association (AEA), the National Education Association (NEA), and the Ohio Association of Public School Adult Educators (OAPSAE), a chapter of the national organization (NAPSAE). Adult education (by state) has material specifically related to adult education in New York, Ohio, Pennsylvania, West Virginia among others. General topics contains miscellaneous pamphlets on topics other than adult education. The folders within each group are arranged alphabetically.
Topics of particular interest include the AEA; educational television and radio; leadership training; community development; and the United Nations & UNESCO. Some materials, especially those dating from the 1920s and 30s, bear Dr. Herschel W. Nisonger's imprint. Dr. Nisonger was Hendrickson's predecessor at Ohio State.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Dowling, William D.; Hendrickson, Andrew, 1899-; Holden, John Bernard.; Houle, Cyril Orvin, 1913-; Jensen, Glenn S.; Kempfer, Homer.; Knowles, Malcolm Shepherd, 1913-; Kreitlow, Burton W.; Long, Fern.; Luke, Robert A.; Nisonger, Herschel Ward, 1890-; Rochte, Newton C.; Verner, Coolie.; The Ohio Adult Observer.; Adult education -- Ohio.; Adult education -- United States.; Older people -- Education.; Educators -- United States.; Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; Reports.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Andrew Hendrickson, 1969 and 1971.
Inventory
The following is a shelf list. Minimal processing has been done on this collection.
- Correspondence
  - 1937-1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948
    - Jan-Jul (Box 1)
    - Aug-Dec (Box 1)
  - 1949
    - Jan-Mar (Box 1)
    - Apr-Dec (Box 1)
  - 1950
    - Jan-Jun (Box 1)
    - Jul-Dec (Box 1)
  - 1951
    - Jan-May (Box 2)
    - Jun-Dec (Box 2)
  - 1952 (Box 2)
  - 1953
    - Jan-Jun (Box 2)
    - Jul-Dec (Box 2)
  - 1954
    - Jan-May (Box 2)
    - Jun-Dec (Box 3)
  - 1955
    - Jan-Apr (Box 3)
    - May-Aug (Box 3)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 3)
  - 1956
    - Jan-Apr (Box 3)
    - May-Aug (Box 3)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 3)
  - 1957
    - Jan-Mar (Box 4)
    - Apr-Jul (Box 4)
    - Aug-Oct (Box 4)
    - Nov-Dec (Box 4)
  - 1958
    - Jan-Apr (Box 4)
    - May-Aug (Box 4)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 5)
  - 1959
    - Jan-Feb (Box 4)
    - Mar-Apr (Box 4)
    - May-Jul (Box 5)
    - Aug-Sep (Box 5)
    - Oct-Dec (Box 5)
  - 1960
    - Jan-Mar (Box 6)
    - Apr-Aug (Box 6)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 6)
  - 1961
    - Jan-Apr (Box 6)
    - May-Aug (Box 6)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 6)
  - 1962
    - Jan-Apr (Box 7)
    - May-Aug (Box 7)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 7)
  - 1963
    - Jan-Mar (Box 7)
    - Apr-Aug (Box 7)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 7)
  - 1964
    - Jan-Jun (Box 7)
    - Jul-Dec (Box 8)
  - 1965
    - Jan-Mar (Box 8)
    - Apr-Jun (Box 8)
    - Jul-Sep (Box 8)
    - Oct-Dec (Box 8)
  - 1966
    - Jan-Mar (Box 8)
    - Apr-Jul (Box 9)
    - Aug-Dec (Box 9)
  - 1967
    - Jan-Feb (Box 9)
    - Mar-May (Box 9)
    - Jun-Dec (Box 9)
  - 1968-1970 (Box 10)
  - Undated (Box 10)
- Writings
  - Articles and addresses
    - 1947-1957 (Box 10)
    - 1959-1968 (Box 10)
  - Pamphlets, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Reports and proposals
    - 1936-1952 (Box 10)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 10)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 10)
    - 1959-1966 (Box 11)
    - 1969 (Box 11)
    - Undated (Box 11)
  - The Ohio Adult Observer
    - 1933-1949 (Box 11)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 11)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 11)
  - Student papers, 1950-1958 (Box 11)
- Miscellaneous
  - Adult Basic Education, workshops, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
  - Adult Education Association, 1968-1971 (Box 12)
    See also Adult education organizations: Adult Education Association (AEA)
  - Biographical information (Box 12)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE)
    See also Adult education organizations: AEA-Commission for Professors in Adult Education
    - 1960-1967 (Box 12)
    - 1968 (Box 12)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 12)
  - Conference on Aging, 1968 (Box 12)
  - Education for Older Persons, 1969-1971 (Box 12)
  - Handbooks and programs in adult education, 1944-1953; 2 folders (Box 12, 13)
  - Meeting papers
    - Minutes
      - 1945-1952 (Box 13)
      - 1953-1957 (Box 13)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 13)
      - 1960-1967 (Box 13)
    - Proceedings
      - 1957 (Box 13)
      - 1958 (Box 14)
      - 1959 (Box 14)
  - Memorabilia
    - Brochures (Box 14)
    - Certificate (Oversize 1)
    - Membership lists and rosters
      - 1947-1957 (Box 14)
      - 1958-1967 (Box 14)
      - Undated (Box 14)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1960; 1971 (Box 14)
    - Photographs (Box 14)
    - Plaques and certificates (Box 19)
    - Programs
      - 1946-1954 (Box 15)
      - 1955-1967 (Box 15)
    - Script, 1960 (Box 15)
    - Speeches, 1965-1970 (Box 15)
    - Various papers, 1961-1968 (Box 15)
    - Unidentified fragments, 1947-1967 (Box 15)
- Adult education - general
  - Continuing education (Box 16)
  - Educational media and methods
    - Home study (Box 16)
    - Radio and TV (Box 16)
    - Other media (Box 16)
  - Educational opportunities
    - Leadership training (Box 16)
  - Publicity (Box 16)
  - Research (Box 16)
- Adult education organizations
  - American Association for Adult Education (AAAE) (Box 17)
  - Adult Education Association (AEA)
    See also Miscellaneous: Adult Education Association (AEA)
    - AEA-Commission for Professors in Adult Education (Box 17)
      See also Miscellaneous: Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE)
  - National Education Association (NEA) (Box 17)
  - Ohio Association of Public School Adult Educators (OAPSAE/NAPSAE) (Box 17)
- Adult education by state
  - Ohio (Box 17)
  - New York (Chautauqua) (Box 17)
  - Pennsylvania (Box 17)
  - West Virginia (Box 17)
  - Other states (Box 17)
- General topics
  - Adult recreation (Box 17)
  - Agriculture (Box 17)
  - Citizenship (Box 17)
  - Community development (Box 18)
  - Family relations (Box 18)
  - Health education (Box 18)
  - Labor (Box 18)
  - Literacy (Box 18)
  - Race relations (Box 18)
  - United Nations/UNESCO (Box 18)
  - Veterans (Box 18)
  - Vocational education (Box 18)
  - YMCA (Box 18)
  - Youth (Box 18)